<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The penniles parliament of threed-bare poets: or, All mirth and wittie conceites</title>
            <title>Jacke of Dover, his quest of inquirie, or his privy search for the veriest foole in England. Part 2.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110366</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845922</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845922</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 969:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The penniles parliament of threed-bare poets: or, All mirth and wittie conceites</title>
                  <title>Jacke of Dover, his quest of inquirie, or his privy search for the veriest foole in England. Part 2.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For William Barley, and are to be sold at his shoppe in Gratious streete neere Leaden-hall gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-A1,C4).</note>
                  <note>Originally published in 1604 as part 2 of: Jacke of Dover, his quest of inquirie, or his privy search for the veriest foole in England.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PENNILES PARLIAMENT OF Threed-bare Poets: OR, All mirth and wittie Conceites.</p>
            <p>PRINTED At London for <hi>William Barley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe in Gratious ſtreete neere Leaden-hall gate. 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:2"/>
            <head>Heere beginneth the Penniles Parliament of threed-bare Poets.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of all, for the increaſe of euery Foole in his humour, wee thinke it neceſſarie &amp; conuenient, that all ſuch as buyes this Booke, and laughes not at it before he hath read it ouer, ſhall be condemned of Melancholy, and be adiudged to walke ouer More-fieldes twiſe a weeke in a foule Shirt, and a payre of Bootes, but no Stockinges.</p>
            <p>It is alſo agreed vpon, that long Bearded men ſhall ſeldome prooue the wiſeſt; and that a Niggards purſe ſhall ſcarce bequeath his Maiſter a good Dinner: and becauſe Water is like to prooue ſo weake an element in the world, that men and women will want Teares to bewayle their ſinnes, wee charge and commaunde all Gardners to ſow more ſtore of Onions, for feare Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes ſhould want moyſture to bewayle their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes Funerals.</p>
            <p>In like maner we thinke it fit, that Red-wine ſhould be drunke with Oyſters: and that ſome Maydens ſhall bluſh more for ſhame, then for ſhamefaſtnes: But men muſt haue care, leaſt conuerſing too much with Red-Petticoates, they banniſh their Haire from their heads, and by that meanes, make the poore Barbers beggers for want of worke.
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10854:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſhall know his owne father.</p>
            <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be lawfull for ſome to haue a Pal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>have more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Pay for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Wife from their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome ſuch a ſtopping in their Hearts, as they ſhall be vtterly obſtinate to receiue Grace: ſome ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as they ſhall be enemies to good counſell ſome ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Moſes, as no Feaſt ſhall eſcape without their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: and ſome ſhall be ſo Needy, as neither Young Heyres ſhall get their owne, nor poore Orphans their Patrimonie.</p>
            <p>Alſo, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Decreed, that ſome ſhall be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they cannot Step but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome ſo conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they ſhall keepe neuer a good thought to bleſſe themſelues: ſome ſo diſguiſed in purſe, as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it fatall to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one Penny to buy their dinners on Sundayes: ſome ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, as they cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t wrong faſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of their occupation.</p>
            <p>But amongſt other Lawes &amp; Statutes by vs heere eſtabliſhes, we thinke it moſt neceſſary and conuenient, that Pou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſhall kill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Poultry by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, thou their. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> May<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es can ſell with a Good Conſcience: alſo it is ordered and agreed vpon, that B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Woodmongers, But thers, &amp; Bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers, ſhall fall to a mighty Conſpiracie, ſo that no Man ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:10854:3"/>
either haue Bread, Fire, Meat, or Drinke, without c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite or ready Mony.</p>
            <p>Sicaphants by the Statute ſhall haue great giftes, and Good and Godly Labours ſhall ſcarce be worth thanks: it is alſo thought neceſſary, that Maides about midnight ſhall ſee wondrous viſions, to the great hart-griefe of their Mothers.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it is marked &amp; ſet downe, that if Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers plead poore mens cauſes without mony, weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Hall ſhall grow out of cuſtome, to the great impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſhing of al Nimmers, Lifters, &amp; Cutpurſes. Thoſe that ſing baſes ſhall loue good drinke by authority: and Trumpeters that ſound trebles ſhall ſtare by cuſtome: Women that weare long Gownes, may lawfully rayſe ouſt in March: and they that keepe a Temperate Dyet ſhall neuer die on ſurfets.</p>
            <p>In like manner it ſhall be Lawfull for Saylors and Souldiers, to ſpend at their pleaſures, what they get by their Sword: and if the Treaſurer pay them any thing beyond count and reckoning, if they buyld not an Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall therewith, they may Beſtow it in Apparrell by the ſtatute.</p>
            <p>It is further eſtabliſhed and agreed vpon, that they that drinke too much Spaniſh Sacke, ſhall about Iuly be ſerued with a <hi>Fiery faces:</hi> but Oh you Ale-knightes, you that deuour the Marrow of the Mault, and Drinke whole Aletubs into Conſumptions; that ſing Queene <hi>Dido</hi> ouer a Cup, and tell Strang Newes ouer an Ale pot: how vnfortunate are you, who ſhall Piſſe out that
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10854:4"/>It is further agreed vpon and eſtabliſh, that many ſtrange euents ſhall happen in thoſe houſes, where the Mayde is predominant with her Maiſter, and wants a Miſtreſſe to looke narrowly vnto her.</p>
            <p>Alſo we thinke it conuenient, that ſome ſhall take, their Neighbours bed for their owne: ſome the ſeruant for the Maiſter: and (if Candles could tell tales) ſome will take a Familiar for a flea. Alſo we thinke it meete, that there ſhould be many Fowlers, who in ſtead of Lackes will each Lobcokes: and many for want of wit ſhall ſell their Freehold for Tabacco pipes, and red pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticoats. Likewiſe we thinke it conuenient that there ſhould be many Takers; ſome would be taken for wiſe men, who indeed are very Fooles: for ſome will take crake Angels of poore debters, and a quart of Malmeſie when they cannot get a pottle.</p>
            <p>But ſtay a while, whether are we carried, leauing the greateſt Lawes vnpubliſhed, and eſtabliſhing the leſſe; therefore we enact and ordaine as a neceſſary Statute, that there ſhall great contentions fall betweene Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Archers, and if the fray be not deſided at a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of Ale and a blacke Pudding, great bloodſhed is like to enſue: for ſome ſhall maintaine that a Turke can be hit at twelue ſcore Pricks in Fiendsbury fields, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the bow and ſhafts wan <hi>Bullen:</hi> other ſhall ſay that a Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun is a dangerous weapon againſt a Mudwall, and an enemy to the painters worke: amongſt theſe controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies wee will ſend forth our commiſſion to God <hi>Cupid,</hi> being an Archer, who ſhall deſide the doubt, and prooue that Archery is Heauenly, for in meditation thereof, he hath loſt his eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10854:4"/>Oh gentle fellow Souldiers, then leaue your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies if you loue a Woman, for I will proue it, that a Mince Pie is better than a Musket; and he that dare gaine-ſay me, let him meete me at the Dagger in Cheape with a Caſe of Pewter-Spoones, and I will anſweare it: and if I proue not that a Mince-pie is the better Weapon, let me Dine twice a Weeke at Duke <hi>Humpheries</hi> table.</p>
            <p>It is furthermore eſtabliſhed, that the foure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at the Cardes, ſhall ſodainely leape from out the bunch, and Deſperately Pranke about the new Play-houſe, to ſeeke out their old Maiſter Captaine Crop-eare: alſo it is thought meete, that ſome men (in theſe daies) ſhall be polliticke beyond reaſon, and write more in one line, then they can proue in an age.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it ſhall be Lawfull for ſome to Study which way they may walke to get them a Stomacke to their meat, whilſt other are as carefull to get meat to put in their bellies: likewiſe there ſhall be great perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in the Common-meale of Kitchin-fees, ſo that ſome deſperate Woman ſhall boyle, try, and ſeeth poore tallow to the generall commoditie of all the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Tallow Chandlers.</p>
            <p>Alas, alas, how are we troubled to thinke on theſe dangerous times? for Taylors, by Act of Parliament may Lawfully inuent new faſhions: and he that takes Iriſh Aquauite by the Pint, may by the law ſtumble without offence, and breake his Face: and it ſhall be thought conuenient, that ſome be ſo deſperat bent, as
<pb facs="tcp:10854:7"/>
they ſhall goe into my Lord Maiors Buttery when all the Barrels be full, without either Sword or Dagger about them: many Men ſhall be ſo Ventrouſly giuen, as they ſhall go into Petty-coate lane, and yet come out againe as honeſtly as they went firſt in.</p>
            <p>In like manner it ſhall be lawfull for Tems Water to Clenſe as much as euer it did in times paſt: and if the Brewers of London buy ſtore of good Mault, poore Burgemen at Queene-hiue ſhall haue a whole Quart for a penny: Saint Thomas Onions ſhall be ſold by the rope at Billinſgate by the Statute: and Semſters in the Exchange ſhall become ſo Contionable, that a man without offence, may Buy a Falling Band for twelue pence.</p>
            <p>It ſhall be lawfull for Smithes to loue good Ale, and if it be poſſible to haue a Froſt of three weekes long in Iuly, men ſhall not be afraide of a good ſter at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommer: Porters Baſkets ſhall haue authority to hold more then they can Honeſtly Carry away: and ſuch a Drought ſhall come amongſt Cans at Bartholmew Faire in Smithfeeld, that they ſhall neuer continue long filled.</p>
            <p>The Images in the Temple Chuch (if they riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine) ſhall haue a Commiſſion to digge downe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Croſſe with their Fauchions: and Millers by Cuſtome ſhall haue ſmall mind to Morning Prayer, if the Winde ſerue them in any Corner on Sundaies: Thoſe that goe to Warres and can get nothing, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Home Poore by Authority: and thoſe that Play
<pb facs="tcp:10854:7"/>
faſt and looſe with womens Apron-ſtringes, may chaunce make a iourney for a Wincheſter Pidgion: for preuention thereof, drinke euery morning a draught of <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> and by that meanes, thou ſhalt bee ſure to eſcape the Phyſitions Purgatorie.</p>
            <p>But amongſt all other Decrées and Statutes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s héere ſet downe, wée ordaine and commaund, that thrée thinges (if they bée not parted) euer to continue in perpetuall amitie, that is a Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe in an olde Doublet, a painted Cloath in a Painters ſhop, and a Foole and his Bable.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it ſhall be lawfull for Bakers to thriue by two thinges: that is, Scores well payde, and Millers that are honeſt.</p>
            <p>Phiſitions by other mens harmes, and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes by often Burials.</p>
            <p>Alſo, wee thinke it neceſſarie for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that the Sammon ſhall be better ſoulde in Fiſh-ſtréete, thou the Beere ſhall be at Willinſgate.</p>
            <p>And Hartes-eaſe amongſt the company of Hearbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wines, ſhall be worth as much money as they can get for it by Statute.</p>
            <p>It is further enacted and agreed vpon that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe that runne foure ſcore Myle a foote on a Winters day ſhall haue a ſore thirſt about ſeauen of the clocke in the euening.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10854:5"/>And ſuch as are inclined to the Dropſie, may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cured, if the Phiſitions know how.</p>
            <p>Alſo wée ordaine &amp; appoint, that (if there be no great ſtore of Tempeſtes) two halfee-peny loaues ſhall be ſold for a penny in White-chappell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chaueers</hi> Bookes (by act of Parliament) ſhall in theſe dayes, prooue more wittie then euer they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: for there ſhall ſo many ſodaine, or rather ſodden Wittes ſteppe abroad, that a flee ſhall not friſke foorth, vnleſſe they cemment on her.</p>
            <p>O what a deteſtable trouble ſhall be among women about foure ſcore and ten yeares olde, for ſuch as haue more Téeth about them, then they can well vſe, ſhal die for age, if they liue not by miracle.</p>
            <p>Alſo it ſhall be lawfull for Bées, if the Sommer ſhew not, to goe on Pilgrimage, and fly ſo farre in one day, as who ſo ſets vp a land marke wheye the firſt light, ſhall come to vs and haue a pound waight of Gold for his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and labour.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, wee thinke it neceſſarie, that thoſe that haue two eyes in their head, ſhall ſometimes ſtumble: and they that can neither write nor read may as boldly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare themſelues, as they that can.</p>
            <p>And it ſhall be lawfull for Almanacke makers, to tell more lyes then true tales.</p>
            <p>And they that goe to Seas without Victuals, may
<pb facs="tcp:10854:5"/>
ſuffer peunurie by the Statutes.</p>
            <p>In like manner, it ſhall be lawfull for any man to carry about him more Golde then Iron: if hee can get it?</p>
            <p>But they that are giuen to ſullen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion (if they be Females) muſt be more circumſpect: for if they repent their hidden ſinnes too much, they may chaunce catch heauen for their labour.</p>
            <p>Therefore let Maydens take heede how they fall on their backes leaſt they catch a fourtie weekes fauour.</p>
            <p>And he that hath once married a Shrew and by good chaunce burie her, beware how hee come into the ſtocks againe.</p>
            <p>Further it ſhall be lawfull for thoſe that be Rich, to haue many Friendes: And they that bee Poore, may by authoritie kéepe Money, if they can get it honeſtly.</p>
            <p>Alſo, wée commaund and charge all ſuch as haue no Conſcience, to doe their worſt, leaſt they die in the Diuels debt: As for the reſt they that haue more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney then they néed may helpe their poore Neighbours, if they will.</p>
            <p>In like manner it ſhal be lawfull for ſuch as are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to het that Rewmes to drinke cold drinke. And thoſe that haue a minde to inrich Phiſitions, to be neuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10854:9"/>Alſo, Souldiers that haue no meanes to thriue by playne dealing, may by the Statute ſwallow downe an ounce of the ſtrro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Suttletie euery morning: And if they cannot thriue that wayes, wée thinke it neceſſarie, that foure times in the yeare, they goe a fiſhing on Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie plaine.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, for the benefite and encreaſe of fooliſh Humours, wee thinke it neceſſarie, that thoſe our deare friends which are ſworne true Seruitours to womens Pantables, ſhould haue this order ſet downe, that you ſuite your ſelues handſomely againſt Gooſe feaſt: and if you meete not a faire Laſſe betwixt <hi>Paules</hi> &amp; <hi>Stratford,</hi> that day, wee will beſtow a new ſuite of Satten vpon you, ſo you will beare all the charges.</p>
            <p>But as for your deare firendes and Schollers, thus much wee fauour you, for you ſhall dine vpon Wit by authoritie: and if you pay your Hoſteſſe well: it is no matter though you ſcore it vp till it come to a good round ſumme.</p>
            <p>In like manner, it ſhall be lawfull for Maydes milke to be good Phiſicke for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>b'd heeles: and a cup of Sacks to bedward, a preſent Remedy for the Rhewme,</p>
            <p>Such as are ſicke in the Spring, may take Phiſicke by the Statute: And thoſe that are cold, may weare more Clothes, without offence.</p>
            <p>It is beſt to ride, in long iourneyes, leaſt a man bee wearie with going a foote: And more comely to goe in broken ſtockings, then bare legged.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10854:9"/>Further it ſhalt be lawfull for ſome to be leaue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Some by the Statute, ſhall loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing well, becauſe they can come by no other meales and other ſome ſuper it with an Egge at dinner, that dare a manfully ſet vpon a ſhoulder of Veale in the after<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Some ſhall be ſad when they want Money: and in loue with Widowes rather for their wealth, then their honeſties.</p>
            <p>It is alſo thought neceſſarie, that ſome ſhall ſuſpect their Wiues at home, becauſe they themſelues play falſe abroad.</p>
            <p>And ſome loue Bowling Allies better then a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <p>But aboue all other thinges, Spirits with Aprons ſhall much diſturbe your ſléepes about midnight.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, it ſhall be lawfull for him that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries without Money, to finde foure bare Legges in his Bed: And hée that is too prodigall in ſpending, ſhall die a begger by the Statute.</p>
            <p>In like manner wée thinke it neceſſarie, that he that is plagued with a curſt wife, to haue his pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> broke quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, as he payes his rent.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, hee that delights in ſubtiltie, may play the Knave by cuſtome: And hee that hath his complexion and
<pb facs="tcp:10854:6"/>
courage ſpent, may eate Mutton on Faſting dayes by the Lawe.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, ſince there are ten Precepts to bee obſerued in the Arte of Scoulding, wee humbly take our leaue of <hi>Duke Humfries</hi> Ordinarie, and he take vs to the Chappell of <hi>Ill Counſaile</hi> where a quart or two of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne <hi>Trinidado,</hi> ſhall arme vs againſt the Gun-ſhot of Tonge-mettle, and kéepe vs ſafe from the aſſaults of Sir <hi>Iohn Find-fault, <hi>Vale,</hi>
               </hi> my deare Friends, till my next returns.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London for W. Barley, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop, in Gratious ſtreete. 1608.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10854:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
